[SPEAKER_00]: So, I wanted to talk about the phenomenon of attraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, the beautiful object in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why are we attracted to that which is beautiful?
[SPEAKER_00]: And I thought about...
[SPEAKER_00]: I came up with an analogy.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, imagine, well, I'm sure many people experience this when you go into a toilet.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, I would like visit a friend's house and you go into a toilet after someone has used it and they've sprayed some air freshener.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know why they sprayed it and it highlights that fact.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, no matter what lavender smell is there, for you, you know the underlying smell of feces.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't kind of ignore it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can try, obviously, but it's like the person who sprayed it,
[SPEAKER_00]: You kind of can more easily ignore that underlying smell.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like they focus on that... those fragrances and then they move on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the next person that comes in, he kind of knows the context of that spray.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... and it highlights that smell underneath.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can't... and then the lavender smell is not the same anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you start associating...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, you have to buy a different air freshener.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I think that highlights the fact that, you know, any beautiful object is only... Why are we attracted to a beautiful thing?
[SPEAKER_00]: What makes it so valuable?
[SPEAKER_00]: And I thought that its value is that it tries to, at least, or it does, cover up something, a bad smell.
[SPEAKER_00]: It covers up a larger context of, I'm suffering here.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I chase something pleasant, I go after the beautiful, because it helps me ignore the the pain that I'm going through.
[SPEAKER_00]: Helps you escape from it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, I think that's the... the Buddha did say that, Sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Putujana does not know any other escape from any reason, unpleasant feeling, other than sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why... that's why it's like not...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not as optional as many people might think.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, you know, I could give this up.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not necessarily attached to the sense pleasures and stuff, because it feels like, yeah, I can go without things and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's only true up to a certain extent, because, yes, there is the kind of a preferential add-on to the whole experience of centrality.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, like a proliferation of preferences and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's all driven by an underlying existential need to go in that direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you don't, there is this underlying pressure of dukkha that you are confined with, that you don't know escape from.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why often a mere idea of giving up sensuality is frightening to people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's when you realize.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you start toying with the idea, that's when you realize
[SPEAKER_01]: How non-optional it really is, your dependence on sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like a need, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might have options developed on top of that need, but fundamentally it's a need, because it's the only form of escape that you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like for the same reason, basically, people then, generally speaking, it's like
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, they would try to find a way around it, to not have to do it, because the... just the thought of not having an escape from suffering, the only one that you know, now leaves you really, like, with a... with an acute kind of recognition of that, as I said, confinement, because, oh, the only means of escaping that I knew, I was told they don't work, now what I'm left with is like a complete confinement with
[SPEAKER_01]: With my own existence, dukkha and so on, that... well, I don't know what to do with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's kind of can be quite trapping for the mind and scary.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why whenever the Buddha was teaching lay people, you know, and they stumbled upon him in conversations, he would give them like a progressive talk.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, he would be guiding their mind rightly towards, you know, seeing the dhamma and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he would always start with first uplifting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because
[SPEAKER_01]: What's about to follow, it's gonna crush it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if it's uplifted slightly higher, then when it's kind of brought down, it won't be like way too depressed, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be right at the right level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, the Buddha could do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, all of the suttas explicitly say that.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Lord saw that their mind is ready, and then he taught them at the right time, to the right extent, guiding their mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And people can kind of gloss over that sometimes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like not a big deal, but it's a huge deal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the fact that
[SPEAKER_01]: Without the Buddha's guidance, you need to meet all those prerequisites and requirements just to be... maybe have a possibility to see the signs of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how deeply people do not see their mind for themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you need to be like fully withdrawn from centrality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then it says, like, you need to be dwelling in seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're, like, delighting in company, say, even if you're actually dwelling in seclusion, but internally you still have delight towards mere association with people, talking, seeing people, that will be an obstacle to see the sign of the mind, which is then the obstacle to sotāpati.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, those are prerequisites for the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, you gotta make... do all the work just to come to the point to see your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: For that mind to become a reference of, you know, whether to tighten or loosen the strings and all those other symbolism.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, obviously, people that met the Buddha were fortunate for one reason or the other, and he guided their mind without them even seeing their mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then they saw it, sure, and when they would exclaim, oh, it's like turning upside... what was upside down, turning it right, what was first place, second, what second place, like correcting the... what was always there, but without his guidance, they wouldn't have been seen.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when the Buddha would talk about the perils of sensuality and so on, it's not about, like, to shame a person or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's nothing to do with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just the fact that, if the mind still relies upon sensuality, the entire domain of sensuality, the possibility of sensuality, as means of escaping suffering, deep down, it's never gonna take on that suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because in order to really understand, to correctly understand what the cause of suffering is, you need to take it on.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just not an option to, oh, I'll avoid it and somehow it's going to get resolved by itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for as long as you're giving in to the ways of avoiding that confinement of the dukkha, seeing the, you know, the four great mountains coming from all directions, as the Buddha would say, recognizing the situation,
[SPEAKER_01]: The opening amidst that confinement will never become apparent.
[SPEAKER_01]: The opening as in the right view, the direction that really takes you out of the whole, frees you from the whole picture.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not about like, oh, you should... you're a bad person or something, if you're still attracted to sense objects and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's way subtler and past any moral judgment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Moral judgments are on the level of five precepts, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, presumably, if you want to train your mind to the point that you can actually see it correctly, to the point that you can develop cittanimitta, which is a prerequisite for the right view, then it's like, okay, you gotta take these on, these trainings, these confinements, for the sake of kind of
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, preventing the mind from spilling in the direction where it shouldn't be spilling towards, and then you get to be left with it, the way it is, and with the causes of that suffering right there and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not yesterday, not tomorrow, not because of this, not because of that, but because of the state of mind affected with craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, also that...
[SPEAKER_00]: If you are attracted to a beautiful thing, you're doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are attracted.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a reason for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a reason that is attractive for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the reason is you are...
[SPEAKER_00]: Uncomfortable here, you're suffering here, you can't face it, you're trying... looking for an escape from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you... Well, it doesn't... not necessarily... it doesn't need to be like that kind of relational, in a sense, that whenever you're attracted, it's because you're suffering right there and then, and you're escaping something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, people can genuinely be fine, overall, but still cultivate the attraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's nothing currently there undermining them, in terms of suffering, in terms of a threat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the way you said it, it sounds like whenever you're attracted, it's because something is right there you're trying to escape from.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it might not be an acute suffering, but in general it's a...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an escape from the liability to suffering, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yes, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like a subtle thing and like... well, even just an escape from discontent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Boredom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those things are already these subtle unpleasantness that if you don't escape from, would turn into full-on pressure and anxiety and panic attack.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like the neutrality of my present experience is just too much
[SPEAKER_00]: For the mind to handle, it's like...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's by chasing something beautiful, that is ignored.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's also the chase as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: The chase is the... Having that chase, having that movement, having that activation, pretty much, that's exactly, kind of, already offers... See, the fact that you could move, already implies that you're not as confined as you might have felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, fundamentally, saṅkharas follow immediately after avijja.
[SPEAKER_01]: The movement follows immediately after ignorance and it proliferates that ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, I guess, interesting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, so, just thinking about the chase.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, chasing some attractive object or beautiful object, chasing it, you know, helps with ignoring of the greater context, perpetuating, which doesn't change that thing in the background, that you are the reason for your chase.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, when you get to that, when you get that pleasant thing that you're chasing, whatever it might be,
[SPEAKER_00]: That background context remains there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, nothing has changed, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now the chase has stopped.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you've got to find a new one.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, you're running out of options.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, you have to keep on diversifying your chases.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, you're running out of options and also your senses, your sense organs are aging, disintegrating, which means sights will be harder to see, sounds will be harder to enjoy,
[SPEAKER_01]: Taste won't offer as much of a relief as before.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, you won't be able to to be distracted on account of sense objects, because your senses cannot appreciate them as much as before.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just aching, failing, not as good as it was, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's also like an impending thing in the direction where you're heading.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, if you are noticing or you understand that
[SPEAKER_00]: I would say, if you understand that a thing is attractive, and it's that the beautiful, the value in that beautiful thing, is to chase, because it covers up your discontent now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you don't chase that thing, and you understand that you are actually discontent here and now, that's why you... That's why you'll be going...
[SPEAKER_00]: Attracted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that getting that thing doesn't actually resolve the issue of your resistance to this discontent here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it does offer a relief, though.
[SPEAKER_00]: It offers a relief, but not...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not just like, oh, it's... nothing is real, it's not true.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensuality offers a factual relief.
[SPEAKER_01]: Chase offers a factual relief through distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just that you need to recognize and convince yourself rightly that those reliefs are actually making things worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not truly relieving you.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're giving you a temporary kind of cover-up, but at the expense of making the whole condition worse, like scratching the...
[SPEAKER_01]: The itch relieves you, factually relieves you, factually makes you feel, ah, now it's better.
[SPEAKER_01]: The itch is gone, but it's making the whole skin condition a lot, a lot worse, so it's gonna itch even harder next time.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the time will come when you won't be able to scratch, basically, one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either because your hands don't work or because there's no more things to scratch with.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, that highlights the the danger of the chasing and also the escape.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, like, well, that's the... this is the perpetuation of my problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: What highlights the danger in the escape?
[SPEAKER_00]: Knowing that, what you just said, you know, that... And what highlights the knowing of that?
[SPEAKER_00]: What highlights it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, what brings it about?
[SPEAKER_00]: Self-reflection.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what brings that about?
[SPEAKER_00]: Dukkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suffering that you basically impose by first and foremost saying no to those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you heard about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could think and ponder all you want and analyze and and and and psychologize and make all the connections.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't give it up first,
[SPEAKER_01]: None of this will have anything to land on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's because sometimes people would think, well, I know I should give it up, and if I ponder hard enough, it will be given up for me, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I meditate rightly, or if I do this rightly, then I'll just lose interest in centrality altogether, without having to just give it up out of faith first.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that will never work.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why even when the when the Arahants wanted, after the Buddha passed away, when they were deciding what to chant first, what to recite first, dhamma or the vinaya, they said, well, there is no dhamma without vinaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: So they spent, I don't know how long, reciting just absolute technicalities of what you shouldn't do, and if you do that, what are the conditions, the whole patimokkha, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, even, even mindlessly, like, as in, like, I have no... any understanding of the right view, the right practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensuality needs to be said no to first.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to be restrained first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you can develop the understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, it's... you could do both at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what you cannot do is not say no,
[SPEAKER_01]: to sensuality as means of existential escape that we just described, and think that pondering about dhamma will somehow do it for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pondering about dhamma without saying no might make you... help you fortify the reasons for eventually saying no to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's only after you say no to it that then you can know, okay, now I am heading in the right direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if I'm still not terribly clear about the nuances of those directions, the fact that the training has been undertaken, means I am heading in the right direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why vinaya means training.
[SPEAKER_01]: Monks' rules, usually, vinaya basically means monks' rules, what they shouldn't do, means training.
[SPEAKER_01]: Since when one undertakes the vinaya, means one undertakes the training of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because it reveals that discontent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you don't necessarily see it or understand it at the time, it brings it up there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't cover it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eventually, you'll have stuff to work with on the right level, because it always has been there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just that you've been, like, too busy immediately, automatically covering it up and just following the directions of distraction and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, the escape... so, you don't... you say no, the danger becomes clear, the escape becomes clearer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, eventually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, things become clearer.
[SPEAKER_01]: You say no, and then the confinement becomes clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Confinement, yeah, and... Because now you're left with, like, with just an intense pressure to just, well, yeah, run, go back to the wilderness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the elephant has been caught.
[SPEAKER_01]: For for at least a certain amount of time, all that is going to think about is its wilderness that has been extracted from.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, when you take on the restraint, training in restraint, yeah, initially, all the mind will think about is things you said no to.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's going to feel worse in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you don't open the gates, if you don't lower the fences, then it will come down within that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you get to see that the whole urge towards that wilderness was the reason you were going into the wilderness.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, if the arising of sensuality in your mind, sensual desire, that's the word I was looking for, if the arising of desire in your mind was not already, in and of itself, unpleasant,
[SPEAKER_01]: You would have never gone to the lengths and pursuits of sense objects as you used to do, as you would be doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if the arising of desire is neutral, well, it ends there and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the arising of desire already hurts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean, like, restraint reveals that sensuality is actually painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: But unless you're restrained, whenever sensuality arises with that pain, you project it onto the sense objects, like, oh, it hurts because I don't have that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then you go for it to appease the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact is, it still hurts first.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the sensuality is factually unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sense desire is factually unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter the amount of pleasure you gain on top of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always going to be driven by the pain of the desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if desire were not painful, well, you wouldn't be moving with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: There would be no activity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It wouldn't be a desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you even conceive any desire that's not slightly uncomfortable?
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't carry that thread of discomfort that you're trying to basically escape, run away from.
[SPEAKER_00]: Appease.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, seeing that and not, no longer resisting the discomfort, then what value has beauty?
[SPEAKER_00]: And what, what is the problem with, you know, you're no longer, if you're no longer resisting your discontent, your dukkha here, then
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no need for a beautiful thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, eventually, the whole, yeah, the whole beautiful things are seen for what they are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Escape from the pain that they inflicted upon you in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a vicious, it's a vicious cycle, exactly like a, like an addiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only reason you go back to drugs is because you've been taking them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you need to go back to them, because you've been taking them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop taking them, you won't be going back to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But time has to pass until the mind calms down away from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there is no other way to go about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: How much you're gonna suffer on account of it, depends how wild your mind was to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people's minds were not that wild, and when they impose the level of that kind of an infinite notion of I will never go back to these things,
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind panics a little bit, but it calms down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people, it just goes into full-on panic attack, like, like, too hard to bear, but... You have to go through it, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you have to go through it, like, and if it's too much, again, you do it gradually, you'll fail, you go back to it, but at no point should you allow yourself to develop views that, I don't have to go through it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because even if you just put everything else aside from the suttas, just take the sheer amount of similes that the Buddha gave about taming the elephant or the thoroughbred horse and the colts and stuff, and just think about the principles of training a wild animal, and you'll see it always boils down to that, and there is no way around it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The elephant, used to the wilderness, roaming where he wants, doing what he wants, will resist, kick and scream, urinate and defecate, as the suttas say, until he calms down when being trapped.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, when it comes down, that's okay now.
[SPEAKER_01]: We can begin to, like, offer it food, take it for a walk.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, you could begin to train it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But trying to train, trying to command and tell elephant what to do, while it's still allowed to roam in the wilderness, well, that's just like talking to a... to a rock or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no communication there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, would you... would you say, then,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I think one thing to add would be, like, you know, if a person hears this, it's like, yes, there's an imperative you must abandon sensuality, but it's not something that you must, or you even can, do it overnight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, okay, from tomorrow onwards, never again, and then I'll be a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to recognize, well, you could try, from tomorrow onwards, never again, and then see what happens tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, when your mind gets... when that elephant wakes up and wants to go back to the... what it's used to, the pastures and stuff, see what force comes up, how forceful it is, most likely you're gonna fail.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: To recognize that it's not about, like, as I said, a moral commandment, it's about training.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, five precepts, add celibacy, add more precepts gradually, but it's all about the training.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about
[SPEAKER_01]: Preventing that mind from spilling into these unwholesome wildernesses and ways of basically existing, they were covering up.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were covering up the dukkha, covering up the source of dukkha, covering up discomfort, and just keeping it dependent on that constant roaming about, emotional.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want this, I want that, I want this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if there is nothing left for me to do or go, then the panic sets in and anxiety comes up and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, you want to address that before that actually comes, before the elephant is too old to move and stuff, but the mind still wants to go and do all of these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then now you're just being, well, like the old king in that sutta, when he would have said, well, I'm
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he asked him, like, what would you do if I tell you there's a big army coming from the east?
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, well, I'll go and fight them there.
[SPEAKER_01]: From the west, I'll go and fight them there.
[SPEAKER_01]: What if I tell you they're, like, coming from all directions?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, sorry, no, it wasn't the big army.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was the... What if I tell you there's a big mountain coming from the east?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, crushing all things... Crushing all things in its way, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he says, well, I would run to the west.
[SPEAKER_01]: What if I tell you there's a mountain coming from the west?
[SPEAKER_01]: No,
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's actually heading towards the destruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, he says, well, in that case, I would give up the lay life and practice the dhamma, well, because the time is short.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like... so, that... that recognition, that... that... that principle, that framework, that... there is no... as I said, there's no changing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can recognize your current limitations and then start working on your environment.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would then support
[SPEAKER_01]: you training in the precepts more, they would then, obviously, calm down the mind gradually, more and more and more.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, don't expect, like, to just magically resolve, because you have such a strong determination, and take it over, like, next day, take on all the precepts, and sense restraint, and then the mind will just magically follow.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's going to be
[SPEAKER_01]: Ups and downs, but the most important thing is that your view and the value of doing it doesn't change.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't, halfway through, convince yourself, no, I don't actually have to keep the priest, no, I don't actually have to... No, you don't need to give these things up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, deep down, you know that you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just, you don't want to believe it, because it's too uncomfortable, and you don't want training to be about going through that discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want it to be about something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's just now... becomes delusional, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as I was saying, like in the beginning, that the fact that you are attracted, you understand all these things to some degree, the fact that you are attracted reveals that there is a problem, that the mind is still... there is some resistance right here to something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, at that kind of stage, so to speak, or whatever, attraction reveals the issue.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a kind of revealing issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, saying no to attraction would reveal the issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Saying no to attraction, I'm not... Because if you're still going with it...
[SPEAKER_00]: I know I'm attracted, but I'm not going towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if I go towards it, of course, yeah, then I'm ignoring the...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm trying...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm covering things up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But knowing attraction is there, and not saying no to it, it highlights the fact why it's there, why it has such a pull.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there's a push here, away from just boredom, neutrality, or pain, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Confinement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, confinement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is dukkha, already form of dukkha, yeah?
[SPEAKER_00]: And that, as that sutta, one sutta says, that if you stop delighting in... you get rid of the light, that craving, then beautiful things in the world just remain as they are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: The things haven't changed, but you just completely overcome your desire towards them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you stop running out from confinement, that... that patiga of your own existence, you stop running away from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you stop running away from it, the purpose
[SPEAKER_01]: Depending on all these beautiful things and using them for distraction, that completely evaporates.
[SPEAKER_01]: The value is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the reasons for engaging with sensuality are gone now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's no need for movement of the sensual kind through the desire.